we have to start moving through new
gardener because as usual organized
behind I'm still on homework number two
I'm on question six
the question is I'll tell you the
question what's an easy shortcut once we
have decided that the looker is not a
looker naturally okay they are not
coming from themselves okay like the
husband is not coming from me and so the
looker is not coming from them so once
you decide the person who's looking
let's say at a blue cup or something
once you decide they are not coming from
their own side okay there's a shortcut
for the other five things what's the
other five things the blue car the
eyeballs cells they awareness of the
blue yeah me yeah I am seeing okay and
then the whole process of seeing okay so
we've been working we've been focusing
on the the meet the looker there's two
lookers really there's the I is looking
and then there's me is looking right so
if not and they are all dependent on
each other you see like I don't know a
pile of books okay like the the second
book is resting on the first book okay
here's the object and the eye is resting
on the object and the awareness of blue
is resting on the eye in the awareness
of me seeing blue is resting on the
awareness of the blue you can say there
might be a witness in the background
resting on dusk and then the whole act
of seeing blue is resting on on all of
them
so okay if you pull out this one they're
all gonna fall down if there's no blue
then there's no eyeball change cells
there's no awareness of blue there's no
thinking I'm seeing blue there's no
witnesses think who listens to I see
blue and there's no scene okay so any
one of them if you can prove it's not
coming from its own side they all must
be not coming from their own side got it
if you pull the book out and sorry the
blue cup out then the other ones go buh
buh buh boom they all fall down because
you cannot have a relationship between a
thing that does come from its on site
and a thing that doesn't come from its
on site let's take it to the kitchen
okay can the wife who doesn't come from
her own son get angry at a husband who
does come from his own site no
impossible one of them doesn't exist
garden in English we say it takes two to
tango you can't have a dance without two
people okay
okay I'll say it again you let's say you
want to dance okay with your wife or
your husband or your girlfriend you're
broken and one of the dancers comes from
their own side they are angry because
they had they didn't get dinner and they
had traffic and the boss yelled at them
okay
did that other dancer is happy because
they told their kids how beautiful they
are okay not because they had a good
meal okay those are not the real reason
for happiness right Tomlin is the real
reason for happiness darling so you
cannot have a dance between two people
one of them is coming from themselves
and one of them is coming from their
past seats okay you can't have one thing
that comes from seeds dancing with
another person who
the income from seeds it's not possible
one of them has to be wrong okay
Gannon if one thing comes from seeds
everything comes from seeds if one thing
doesn't come from anything accepts this
then everything else is the same
that's the way to cheat if you don't
want to spend a lot of time in class
because it gets like I don't have to
come to class anymore why well you
already proved the looker is not coming
from their own side everything else is
saying everything else in say or they
cannot touch each other or they cannot
touch each other got it
if one of them is missing then the other
ones fall down okay if if the looker is
not coming from their own side then the
blue can't come from their own son then
they I can't come from their own side
then they I can't come from its own side
then the thinking about the I can't come
from its own sign then the act of seeing
cannot come from and so I got it because
they all depend on each other they are
all piled up like books they are like
two dancers okay if one of the two
dancers doesn't come from their own side
then the other one cannot come from
their own side because they're dancing
they have a relationship if the things
are completely different they can't have
a relationship okay
in the kitchen what does it mean if the
husband is coming from the seeds of what
I did with my kids then the wife who
sees the husband has to be coming from
seeds or garden the or hasta cannot see
each other they cannot have a
relationship if one of them exists
through admin to staff nature and one of
them doesn't they can't see each other
one of them can cannot be garden so
that's if you're late in the homeworks
and you have to get to the next class
quickly you don't have to prove the blue
is not coming from Sun side and the eye
is not coming Renaissance and the
awareness
and the awareness awareness is not gonna
say you just say look it's all the same
or else they couldn't be related to each
other okay got it
you're awful quiet I'll say it one more
time okay I'll say it one more time
let's take it to the kitchen okay it
looks like the husband is upset for the
same reason that all men get upset they
didn't eat you know that those married
people know that how to shut the husband
up just cook something okay I go to the
kitchen I'm like this you know how you
doing really good so she says I know
you're hungry just come back later
it's coming we have a deal she does
mostly cooking and I do all the dishes
it's dependent relationship so by the
way if you're having marital problems
the men the easy way to fix a marriage
problem is if the man wash the dishes
all the time then there's no marriage
problems okay I'm just telling you the
women paid me to say that okay but it's
true it's really as far as I know it's
true okay so look if the husband is not
upset because he didn't eat or you know
he got trouble at his job but he looks
upset because I yelled at my kids last
week okay and the husband's coming from
my seats okay then I if I can meet the
husband in the kitchen then I must also
be coming from seeds garden once you
prove the husband comes from seeds you
don't have to talk about where the
kitchen came from of course it came from
seeds or
the husband couldn't stand in in a
husband who didn't come from seeds
cannot stand in a kitchen which did come
from States got in either everybody
comes from seeds and the kitchen or
nobody comes from seeds so if you want
to prove the kitchen came from seeds
just prove the husband came from seeds
then by the way you also prove you came
from since and you prove meeting your
husband came from since right mind only
school got it
you okay it's too quiet in here if one
thing in this whole story blue awareness
of blue eyeball me looking at the blue
me looking at me looking at the blue
there looking at the blue if one of them
comes from seeds all of them come
Frances okay then you can just go to the
next homework okay we're moving on to
chapter 4 if you give me the sanskrit
word for the subject of chapter 4 you
get twenty dollars ten tonight you have
to raise your hand nine wait wait raise
your hand this is the hand
this is raised okay go look uh Skanda
Skanda okay good it's gonna he heaps
okay he's so person the fourth chapter
now we made big progress how many
chapters we have to finish six in six in
this session in this ten days or
whatever so we're not to the second
chapter okay
third chapter was called in sanskrit you
can say indriyas okay the powers we are
investigating the powers for twenty
dollars
does the third chapter investigate the
powers or not
for $20
that's the third chapter investigate
their powers or not well once okay yeah
but that's not the answer
hmm are we investigating the powers the
name of the chapter is investigating the
powers are we investigating the Paras
yes
what are we investigating the stupid guy
did you say stupid guy no I
okay well she said it for you you get
$20 good job
that's what nuns are so good yeah we are
investigating the stupid guy what does
stupid guy say I forgot what do you say
about the blue in this all that it comes
from its own thing yeah why Buddha
taught it come on it's one of the first
teachings he ever gave in the abhidharma
okay if the blue doesn't come from its
own sign then the blue is not real then
the Buddhist teaching fantasies you know
then the Buddha must have been drunk
when he taught the power okay if it's
not real if the blue is not real the
Buddha must have been mistaken
okay that's his problem that's he said
look it's fundamental teaching I'll be
done with teaching okay Buddha taught it
if it's not if the blues not real if you
say the blues not real then the Buddha
has the blues now if you say the blue is
not real then the Buddha was wrong okay
is that true statement it is a true
statement if the Buddha taught about
blue and blue isn't real then the Buddha
is mistaken okay
did the Buddhists say blue wasn't real
he never said that he said fake reality
it's real you can look at it you can
have a blue car it's real okay got it
but it comes from you right okay so his
accusation if you say blue is not real
Buddhist mistaken we said no we never
said the Blues not real you said it's
fake yeah we said it's fake but how can
it be real it's fake real okay it's not
what you thought
thank means it's not what you thought it
was but it's there it's still there okay
so we finished that chapter now we're
going to the next chapter we are going
to look at the parts of a person mm5
parts right first one your physical body
by the way do the five parts of a person
include all the stuff in the world yeah
some smart abhidhamma guys say yes when
you say Skanda number one physical
Skanda it includes this room it includes
the desert and includes the mountains it
includes the sky it's all part of your
experience you are not just where the
skin ends this room is also part of of
you right so they say scan discover
everything okay
first Condor covers the whole world okay
second scan de your feelings third
Skanda discriminate between things first
kinda everything else fifth kinda your
mind okay why didn't they make just
three scanners why don't they make mine
body and other stuff why they divide
them
yeah call away guilty rim Gucci pumpin
um NATO and Russia logic pumashark first
chapter I'll be double question we
divide those two mental functions out
because they cause all the trouble in
the world this person I like this person
is nice that person I don't like this
person is not nice okay we divide people
on basis of our feelings okay that's the
cause of all trouble in the world that's
why there's five parts of person instead
of three okay where do we put all the
other mental functions like love or
intellect or jealousy or contact yeah
yeah put them in pile number four
everything else okay got it
so if I now listen it's on your homework
okay if I ever give it to so how many
basic kinds of stuff into five heaps
three
don't let him answer all the question
okay human computer okay somebody else
to tell me what the three are physical
stuff physical stuff and all the rest
yeah and all the rest okay now The
Guardian is going to the teachings about
the five heaps it feels like because the
accountants are bothering him okay and
don't forget he's the guy who came after
700 years and kicked the accountants out
of the Buddhism room okay
I'll be Dharma died after then who wrote
the greatest book I'll be timer Stanley
Bob under Vasa Bunder
why did he write it say the whole story
okay why did vast bandeau right there
I'll be damned across the greatest book
of a Biederman he used to criticize his
half-brother who is Arya Sangha who is a
higher the Mahayana and then one day he
was sitting in the class taught by his
brother and he realized that Mahayana
teaching is the the real truth and he
wanted to repent and he wanted to cut
his tongue but his brothers I know if
you were to if you were to come over the
whole teaching will die so since you
have such a great knowledge of
abhidhamma why don't you write a
comprehensive discussion of it
abhidhamma
as part of his repent so he doesn't have
to cut his tongue when the abhidhamma
Koecher was written and interestingly he
always pre-start his sentence with they
say they say which is that he doesn't
believe in the content itself good
explanation yeah so but the whole
argument of the other guy in chapter 3
chapter 4 chapter 5 is look this is the
most basic teaching of Buddhism this is
the core foundation of Buddhism all
Buddhism is built on Abaddon so are you
telling me Buddha was wrong are you
telling me in the foundation of our
Buddhism was wrong okay are you telling
me the teaching about sense powers the
twelve ayudarnos was wrong indriya
he's saying that's wrong we finished
that okay
now we're going to the five heaps okay
and we take the most basic one okay
what's the most basic one
it's your physical body okay you spend
most of your time thinking about your
physical body especially if you're man
for two reasons okay and we live in our
physical body we're very attached to our
physical body okay so if that's not real
nothing is real okay if the physical
body is not real then nothing is real so
the guy comes back the accountant comes
back it's okay I get this thing about
your eyeball and the blue I got that I
understand that but what about your
physical body you know that's so
fundamental if it's not real there's
problems and here's the cool part okay
listen chapter who for what the other
guy says is he's not arguing about
physical body okay
he's arguing about what created your
physical body okay got it
there's a difference he's not arguing
about your physical body he wants to
argue about what created your physical
body okay what creates your physical
body okay
and in Buddhism in abhidharma
what composes your body as similar to
science is the elements okay you can
sometimes say the four elements such a
melon or you can say the five elements
such a melon number you can add numpce
okay but we're talking about the four
elements okay the four elements in
sanskrit they are called Buddha said
Buddha
yeah Buddha okay sometimes they're
called Mahabharata okay the big Buddhist
okay got it
so Buddha means element like earth water
Fire and wind okay and again I said many
times but you know in
in western science in the Middle Ages
they believed in the elements fire and
all doctors study the elements and then
they burn you or they take your blood
out and kill you you know they didn't
understand them but they call them the
four elements okay
it comes from Aristotle I guess
something like that but in Buddhism the
idea of the four elements is very
sophisticated okay it's very similar to
quantum physics okay there are basic
energies in the universe that create
physical matter
okay there are powers underneath by the
way there's your Sanskrit word that's
cute
who did that mr. Tim how he has time to
do these things I don't know that's your
second Sanskrit word for today say
Buddha the meaning is an element okay
one of the four elements in this case it
comes from a root called by the way that
slash in sanskrit means this is a root
verbal root there are eight hundred
roots of Sanskrit if you memorize them
you know Sanskrit I used to memorize
them on the bus to New York Sanskrit is
so predictable that a computer can
generate the forms of Sanskrit if you
teach the rules to a computer
it's called generative grammar it will
create Sanskrit language Sanskrit
language is perfect you can teach a
computer the rules and it from any root
it can create the rest of the words so
if you learn them the roots you can
understand any sense without knowing the
word okay so Boo is to be
and it comes in the English word to be
and to build and physics okay
pH often comes from BH it's a Greek the
Greek pH like photon or photography
that's why they they are spelled with pH
they come from the BH okay so physics
comes from boom okay
so Buddha means the elements okay now
chapter 4 is called an investigation of
the parts of a person the skanda parts
of a person but we're going to focus on
the first part of a person and they were
gonna cheat using the dance analogy
what's that mean
yeah if the first heat is dancing with
the other for hips and if the first team
doesn't come from its own side than the
other hips cannot come from their own
side because they are dancing together
there are any side of you you have five
heaps I don't have to prove all five of
them are empty I start to prove one of
them is empty and then the rest if
they're connected they all have to be
empty gun in okay that's a way to not
spend ten years on the gardener just
prove the the most basic one is coming
from your seeds and then the rest must
be conferences because they interact
your mind is on your body what proves it
ulcers and beer for $50 ten nine
it you shut up seven six five four
I love the yoga teacher who goes ten
nine eight seven six five four three two
one stress and getting drunk wait well
who is that
fifty bucks come on you have my you can
take the money honey wait but what did
you say I said stress and getting drunk
good the stress ulcers and getting junk
proofs the body and mind are connected
stress and ulcers and getting drunk
proofs in Buddhism proves that the body
and the mind are connected okay if you
work in a very stressful environment you
get ulcers so you get a heart attack
that proves that the mind affects the
body okay then the opposite yeah if you
put alcohol in the body the mind gets
even more stupid okay what's the word in
Buddhism for alcohol no che say no che
crazy maker make you crazy okay if you
can get drunk if your mind can get
stupid by putting some liquid in your
body then the body and the mind must be
connected if you can get a heart attack
from too much stress I looked up
Veronica's grandfather was the first
Hispanic Congress person in the United
States from New Mexico and he won six
times Congress and then the last time
his name is Antonio Fernandez and he won
his seventh reelection six reelection
and he died the next day they they swear
him to be the congressman he died the
next day because so much stress
from what do you call campaigning under
understand so stress must affect your
body okay that means they're connected
that means if we want to prove every
part of you is empty we just have to
prove your body is empty and that's
where we're going in this chapter okay
got it
we're going to the first gun because
it's the easiest one okay it's the one
that's in front of you all the time okay
all right here we go
[Music]
yeah so again we're just going for the
biggest one if we can prove that's empty
if we can prove that's coming from seeds
then because it has a relationship with
the other ones because if you get drunk
or you get stressed then the others must
be empty also okay all right now what
are we investigating about this okay and
the other guy says okay
and it's abhidharma this is basic I'll
be damned
okay basic abhidharma all physical
matter is two parts all physical matter
has two parts number one there's the
underlying energies quantum physics
there's energies gravitational force
electrical force weak force strong force
electrons protons quarks charm there's
energies that are keeping your body
together they create the cells they
create the molecules and then they
create the big body you see what I mean
so Buddhism says quantum physics says
there are fundamental energies under
your body that are holding up the body
they create the body okay got it all
cells are made of molecules all
molecules are made of atoms all atoms
are made of basic energies fundamental
energies okay so buddhism says the same
thing okay you have four fundamental
energies in your body saw to mainland
say
son chu man no I was gonna give you the
four four for your sanskrit words but it
was too many what geshe-la usually does
is say he says he's gonna teach you
three sanskrit words every day and then
it gives you ten so I actually erased
them but if you want to know the name
for earth water Fire and wind okay in
Sanskrit / TV / TV is earth / TV PIR thi
VI it's not on your homework it's just
for your knowledge okay P I R th I VI /
TV okay that's earth Qiu is up AP up
just AP okay the water element is called
up up up - because the P changes to be
okay up so up means water may in when
you're talking about the elements fire
is Tejas okay they just te Jas then the
usual word for fire Agni but when you're
talking about the four elements it stage
us when do you know from yoga value okay
value okay so those are the four
elements now to understand the gardener
we have to do some abhidhamma I'm sorry
okay to beat the accountants we have to
know what the accountants believe okay
got it
so let's talk about what are these four
elements okay I I say they are very
sophisticated understanding of basic
energies of all physical existence okay
earth okay its function is sour say
summer
how do you want to call it come concrete
okay the energy called
earth is what gives objects solidity
okay it's the energy of solidity okay it
it recall it brings things together
congrat the function earth is not dirt
okay
earth is an energy which conceals things
together you can say it's like gravity
it's like the force of gravity okay it
tends to what do you call it state of
when you call it when the the universe
will reach a state of all particles will
be equally distant from each other in
time entropy okay and the opposite of
that is which brings things together to
make planets to make noises to make
computers is called Earth okay got it
that's the energy called Earth it's not
little particles of dirt that you
sprinkle into your body it's not that
okay it's not vitamins that you eat or
something like that it's not that okay
to water okay Lin Chang Shan wha-what is
that
yeah it's the wet thing and it flows
okay it's fluid did d the principle of
fluidity things flow okay
opposite of entropy again things don't
just stay in one place things tend to
flow okay
things tend to flow and they have a
wetness okay
now interesting thing when you talk
about temperature which is our next one
let's go there okay T just such a me
fire okay fire which means temperature
in in Western physics do all things have
a temperature do they have some warmth
yeah everything has some warmth absolute
zero turn 53 minus
everything has some warmth ice has some
warmth okay because you can make ice
colder you can have colder ice
okay so there's some warmth and now
listen according to Abby Dharma which is
true all four energies are found in all
objects all four energies exist in all
physical objects the table has more
Earth energy than wind energy ok the
wind energy is the what do you call it
it's called young-shin your that's the
entropy force it tears things apart it
tends to break things apart
it tends to be movement out from the
center ok all things have it in the
table the earth element is stronger than
the wind element got it but in time the
wind element will take over the earth
element and this table will fall down
ok got it and medicine ancient Indian
medicine Chinese medicine all based on
these elements okay too much water
element you die of pneumonia too much
fire element you died of a fever balance
is crucial in in medical theory of India
and in China okay
so these are the four elements okay all
all objects have them okay the green
drink is flowing into my mouth because
it has a lot of water element but it
also has fire element because it's not
ice and it also has wind element if you
pour it out it will spread it will flow
water okay so different things are
different elements why are we talking
about that
the first Skanda is
your body okay it's skin bones meat but
underneath them it's the four elements
holding them up okay the four elements
came first and then they created your
skin and they created your bones the
bones have more earth element than the
skin okay as you get older the skin
becomes more like the bones they change
they tend to change okay so the most
fundamental cause and effect in all of
Buddhism is that the four energies the
four elements create your body okay the
most unquestionable caused an effect in
all of Buddhism hundreds of thousands of
books in Mongolia just Mongolia okay but
the most fundamental cause and effect
this something made your body okay for
energies made your body okay the
energies were the cause and the result
was your body okay so all physical
objects in Buddhism according to the
abhidharma
and accepted by all schools is that you
the four energies are below all physical
matter and then they are creating what
we call products of the elements so
there's the elements and there's the
products of the elements God in four
energies and then four products of the
four energies I'm sorry
many product mean eleven nine or four
seven awesome okay anyway things that
you
it's a VI / TV VI yeah the rest are good
okay
change the b2v
which one
no it's P I PR it's the vocalic R / I
just use IR for pronunciation okay / /
tibi okay good that's not on your
homework that's just for free okay okay
so here's a question here we go what's
the most basing okay forget su gang
forget Bucharest okay don't go to the
VIP teaching about the twelve links it's
too much cause and effect it's too
complicated okay I'm just kidding
right there's a more fundamental cause
and effect and it's the body you are
walking around in that's the effect
what's the cause the four energies the
four elements
okay got it you can't find a more
obvious connection than the four
elements and your body and if that
connection is not natural then the
Buddha was a liar if that connection is
not Atman real nature then everything is
false
everything is wrong if your body doesn't
come from stuff then nothing causes
anything okay then the Buddha is a total
liar got it
he's China the other guy's trying to
think what's the most basic kind of
cause and effect in the universe you
know oh it's your own body come on it
comes from chemicals okay
what's the proof of chemicals your duh
you're sitting in it okay where's the
proof of chemicals you're sitting in it
okay the guy is trying to say there are
some things in the world which are
natural they are not coming from karma
they are not coming from seeds they're
out there they're real they're strong
you know I didn't make this with seas
come on it's too hard it was made by
those four energies and that
relationship is natural no one made it
didn't Einstein didn't come and create
cause and effect it was there already
okay got it nobody made cause-effect
right wrong okay if it exists you made
it
okay so got it we're treating the five
parts of a person five skandhas punches
Conda and we're talking about the first
one cuz it's so you sit in it all day
come on and we're saying what are we
saying about it
what's the other guy come in the
beginning of the fourth chapter what
does he say what does he say
what does the accountants thing who are
we investigating he's like come on the
gardener this is natural nobody made
this can we talk about seeds in karma
Buddha taught that this is coming from
my elements this has chemicals you idiot
okay now that guy said now you ready you
are go deeper I'm just setting you up I
by the way that finishes the second
homework yay let's go to a third
homework you knew I was gonna get there
no guard you know how are you doing on
time mmm how much time I have 10:30 okay
ten more minutes then PP okay I promise
you can even put the cause into the
effect
you drink something drink something now
drink something okay you have to think
okay drink always bring something to
drink water element so we finally
reached the fourth chapter we have
someone to investigate okay we have a
criminal thinker okay what does the
criminal thinker say the gardener some
relationships aren't natural
no one made them they didn't come from
seeds they exist from the other side
maybe the husband is coming from me but
the kitchen is not and my own hand is
not okay my own hand is not coming from
me come on
I understand that the yelling of the
husband was created by yelling at my
kids I can handle that but my hand comes
from chemicals okay it doesn't come from
me what I gave people hands or something
that's the other guy okay this Albie
diamond guy
do they have emptiness in Naveed armor
forward hundred dollar question
five four three where two one damn
hundred dollar something
[Music]
[Applause]
only one place in a d-dimer there's this
Massimo emptiness it's not even a real
emptiness in the for hire truth sixteen
aspects he studied it a couple weeks ago
but I thought he would forget York's
expensive friend okay all right now the
guys being investigated who said look I
understand my husband
yelling comes from me but my hand come
on that comes from chemicals we can see
chemicals right we don't have to say
four four elements you can say chemicals
carbon oxygen nitrogen you know in the
West we don't say four four we don't say
fire when we say chemicals my body comes
from right you know I have to eat more
protein my doctor told me I have to eat
more protein I need more of the iron
iron iron we call we have elements we
just call them the periodic chart of the
elements right 113 now it's 220 carbon
oxygen nitrogen good stuff like that
okay we have the same belief okay I
understand my husband's yelling in the
kitchen comes from me yelling at my kids
I can take that but my hand comes from
chemicals elements carbon iron oxygen
okay it's not a figment of my
imagination and the gardener it's too
solid yelling is one thing you know I
understand that's empty
he's his mother comes in she finds the
yelling very appropriate and beautiful
okay right I understand the emptiness of
my husband yelling his mom thinks he's
right I think he's wrong that's
emptiness I understand but come on
hand hand is real hand is real hand is
made by chemicals okay you eat too much
iron the hand will fall apart
you don't need enough iron the hand will
fall apart there must be some connection
okay all right now what's our answer we
have three answers okay this is your
first homework question just repeat it
be like an American college students
just repeat it if you don't understand
it it's okay okay here's Janice
three answers and then we're gonna spend
your post PP brain explaining some of
them okay here are some the Cardenas
answers in the fourth chapter okay the
guy came and said look I understand
about the husband that's okay but my
hand is real and there's a cause and
effect here if I don't eat enough
protein my bones will get weak I I can't
do yoga who's teaching yoga today do I
have to run over is she tough don't
don't ask her boyfriend okay okay maybe
I won't go into your time if you help me
out here and you understand I'm kidding
you teach any class you want the student
when you're a student you have to shut
up and do what the teacher says okay
even if you're a teacher
okay three answers buying a gardener I'm
just gonna tell you the short names
that's the answer to the first homework
question just a short names I don't want
an explanation I just want the short
names okay first shortened name causes
and effects which are really separate
from each other they're not the same
thing
the cup and the glass are separate okay
cause and effect which is separate
that's the first argument the name of
the first argument by the ghajini to the
person who wants to talk about their
hand is look the cause and the effect
are separate
really separate really you have to say
really okay if you don't put really
under homework you you you got it wrong
really suffering this is the four
energies right and this is my hand okay
and this is the cause and this is the
effect okay and this one makes this one
okay but they are separate obviously
okay your hand is not your nitrogen
okay the nitrogen makes the hand carbon
makes the hand okay got it
there's the elements and the products of
the elements cause anything the most
basic causing effect in the universe you
walk around in it all day okay it must
be pretty cause-and-effect II got it
okay so one thing we can say in the
garden us okay ready here's the gardener
oh yeah
is there cause yeah there's the four
elements this the I'll be Dharma guy
okay he always talks like a nerd is
there a cause here that's the gardener
yeah there's the elements yeah is there
a result here yeah there's my hand okay
are they the same thing are they
separate welcome and it gotta be
Stanford okay got it
are they really separate of course if
they're not really separate then they're
really one and they're just my hand
becomes nitrogen and then it flows away
got it okay got it
alright that's the first argument the
gardener's question is he's
investigating right the police tie the
guy to the chair and he said you think
that the elements are separate from the
hand and the guy says uh-huh
there's a really separate mhm mhm okay
that's the first argument second
argument Randy okay you're the guy in
this here okay I'm the police who's the
police the gardener
this is the cause right and these are
the elements and this is your hand okay
ready
do they exist or not I'm talking both or
either doesn't matter do the elements
exist or not exist does the hand exist
or not yeah yeah so the cause exists
yeah
does the result exist yeah really yeah
okay all right so the second one is come
causes and effects which exist or don't
exist and somehow that's wrong okay it's
an accusation of the police you're sick
man
you're criminal you're a bad man why you
believe the cause exist or not exist and
you believe the result exist or not
exist oh you are so bad okay if you are
looking at me like I'm crazy you
understand if it seems normal
you are wrong I'll say it again okay
the gajanan ties the guy Church here the
guys right has his police hat on and
probably a bad time Abed and then you
ask the guy so you believe your hand was
created by the elements yeah yeah yeah
chemicals yeah yeah yeah did those
chemicals exist or not exist it's a
question okay do they exist or do they
not exist is either one true is either
one true I'll say it again the gardener
says about the elements do they exist in
your body or did they not exist in your
body either answer you give is wrong and
your hand is it there or is it not there
either answer the criminal gift is wrong
how to write the question on the
homework guess I just tell me causes and
effects causes and effects which exist
or which don't exist both are wrong both
are wrong okay
the gardener says both are wrong okay
here we go again this is why you got a
ride on your homework
whether you're understanding or not
causes and effects which either exist or
don't exist they're both wrong both are
wrong okay got it
is there anything else besides existing
not exist is it possible to the coffee
is better than an injury I'm just
telling you okay now third question it's
important why if we finish it you get to
pee pee okay here's the third question
asked by the police okay to this guy oh
so you believe those elements comes to
him right and yeah we said that many
times good I said that in the first
teachings Buddha said good okay so let
me ask you something it's the cause
similar to the result or not are the
elements similar to the hand or not okay
are they similar or not and the gardener
what's the garden a thing what's the
police say if you say yes you're wrong
and if you say no you're also wrong it's
just like a discussion with your wife
okay take a break take a ring I'll say
the third one again causes and effects
which are similar or not similar you're
wrong both with you're wrong it's the
perfect police question no matter what
answer you give you go to jail okay
take a break don't worry about it just
do have some up make some up
abductor abductor what's that what's a
cognate for for water oh yeah yeah ah
come on here we go okay so we're gonna
have three arguments against nitrogen
and hen a carbon carbon in here okay
here's the first argument are they
separate or not are they separate or not
what do you think is a seed separate
from the tree I mean what do you think
what comes in your mind I don't know is
the seed separate from the tree feels
like that I mean you got a store to buy
seeds you don't buy trees right and they
put the seeds in a package and you plant
the seed and then a separate tree comes
out right
I mean when you buy a pack of seeds you
don't buy a pack of trees right they're
separate I think so
and they separate ah oh man
you know now you became the police yeah
Lucas as you create the connection
between the seed and the tree okay
here's the gardener and each of these
three arguments he's gonna go both ways
he's gonna go both ways okay which means
if the seed is separate from the tree
there's this problem and then looking at
it from the trees side if the tree is
separate from the scene okay
so he goes both ways is this seed
separate from the tree and it's the tree
separate from the scene okay so in these
three arguments he's gonna go both ways
okay he's gonna look at it from the call
side and then it's gonna look at from
the cheese side what is the cause in
this case they're four elements
yeah the four elements and then your
hand I'm gonna say hand is easy okay
you're okay
then it's very short the homework answer
is very short yay and I'll just read it
to you okay but try to change a few
words this is DCI problem in the right
people paste in copy okay if a result
were truly okay I want to see the word
truly in there I want to see the word
truly in there okay it means
self-existent Lee it means from its own
side you can say really
really I'm gonna pay you back next week
really don't worry word I'm gonna give
you all the money I owe you
next week really really so when you're
the criminal you have to keep repeating
really yeah they are really separate
they are really separate okay
that means there's a difference between
what and what there's a difference
between separate and really separate
okay got it
okay there's a difference between
separate and really separate is the
husband yelling is he no okay so if
you're gonna be a good criminal in this
courthouse called
wisdom you have to keep saying really
okay then you pass your homework okay in
the result we're really separate from
the cause it could exist without the
cost if the tree is really separate from
the scene then the tree doesn't need the
scene cuz it exists separate okay if the
seed and the tree never touch okay if
there are separate things if they never
melt into each other anywhere anytime
then the tree doesn't need the scene
okay cuz they're separate it already
exists on its own okay
separate means on its own right so what
were you what were you thinking you were
thinking the the edge of the seed melts
into the edge of the tree what were you
thinking
when you said they're not separate or
separate you're thinking you know these
kind of people who are born the twins
and they are connected
what do you call Siamese twin they are
connected by the shoulder it's the tree
and the seed like that or are they
separate is it twins or is it Siamese
twins yeah some reason you're correct
because if it's twins one twin can die
in the womb and the other one will
survive okay it happened to one of our
students okay they had twins in the womb
in one of them passed away so they must
be separate otherwise the second twin
will die also right so if the tree if
the hand is really separate from those
energies then the hand can exist without
those energies okay got it okay now
let's go the other way okay if the scene
is separate from the tree then it
doesn't have to give a tree to be a seed
I'll say it again if the seed is really
separate from the tree then the seed
doesn't have to give a tree to be called
a seed seed means it has to give
something right cause you can say cause
if the cause is separate from the result
then the cause can be a cause without
doing anything
guarding okay if they are separate so
guess okay I believe what you say if the
tree is separate from the seed then the
tree can it grow without the scene and
at the seed is separate from the tree
then the seed could be a seed without
ever giving any
it would be a cause without ever giving
a result if the tree and the scene are
not connected okay if they are separate
okay got it
okay and the only other choice is come
some kind of Siamese twin thing you know
the end the the last moment of the seed
is connected to the first moment of the
tree or something like that then is it a
seed or a tree you know when that gets
complicated
okay got it now in the first argument
and this is hard stuff okay if you don't
understand don't worry I also didn't
understand yesterday with the other two
arguments he's gonna say you are wrong
no matter what answer you give he's
interrogating he's what he called
investigating the criminal did you steal
the money if the guy says yes he's gonna
put him in jail if the guy says no he's
still gonna put him in jail okay this in
the gondola system he doesn't do that
with the first argument he does not do
that with the first argument he doesn't
talk about what if they are not separate
he doesn't talk about what if they are
not separate with the other two
arguments he says either answer you give
you're wrong you say yes you're wrong
you say no you're wrong it's just like a
conversation with your husband your wife
got in but in this one the guy says and
the gardener says are they separate or
not the guy says they are then he says
impossible okay he doesn't give the guy
a chance to say they are not separate
okay but in the other two he does all
right you okay you still with me
okay don't be a criminal here Wow we're
making good progress okay now
Nagata says let me let me get this
straight myself yeah okay does the
result exist or not you're the criminal
you look like a criminal just kidding
I'm the police okay like that's the
result exist or not that's the tree
exist or not
well then you don't need a cause sorry
you're right that's the tree really
exist or not
yes or no come on I you guys gotta agree
among yourself they didn't say yes then
you don't need to see why you need to
see this tree exist okay got it
okay really okay by the way who got in
trouble for saying really bubbly vodka
that's another story okay yeah okay if
the trees there then the seed can't do
anything for it and then the seed is not
a sin
okay if the tree is not there then you
don't need a scene you don't have to
talk about anything
there's no reason to talk about scene
for what nothing you know
okay got it if the seeds if the tree is
there
you don't need a sim because he's
already redundant nobody needs him
anymore
there's already a tree we don't have to
respect the state the trees our leader
you go away we don't need you anymore ok
if the tree is not there now understand
ok this is the seed this is the tree ok
so if the tree is there you don't need a
steam because the seed is supposed to
make the tree come but it's too late now
if the tree is not there he doesn't have
anything to do so you don't need him
again ok got it
that's not he has not no work to do
because there's no tree ok
now sometimes they will add the word
does the tree exist at the time of the
scene does the tree exist at the time of
the scene ok if it now listen try to
understand the gardener
what's his what's he saying just before
he arrested the guy what did he say
something going on something's gone
something doesn't make sense you know
he's he's he's like just when you think
I'm the gardener don't think of this you
know are you think of this guy like
it don't make sense something weird
going on what's that
if the listen okay
the seed has to affect the result right
there gotta be some contact it like like
when you play pool billiards like the
first ball has to hit the second ball
there has to be a clunk and in the
second ball goes okay so the see the
seed has to make contact with the tree
has to or nothing's gonna happen
that means the tree has to be there at
the same time when the seed is still
there otherwise the banana which is
rotting in your refrigerator in
Guangzhou right now also create the tree
if they don't have to be in the same
place and make a connection if they
don't have to touch each other then I
don't know Donald Trump's hair is the
cause for the tree because they don't
have to touch they don't have to be in
the same place got it
then anything can be the cause of the
tree you know when you blow your nose
the trees will grow if they don't have
to be in the same place then everything
cause the tree garden if one thing can
cause a tree without being in the same
place at the same time then everything
cause the tree got it
if one thing that's not there can make
the tree grow then why can't everything
that's not there can make the trees grow
what's the difference if if the seed
doesn't have to be around when the tree
grows then everything else in the world
can make a tree go to what's the
difference if one thing that's not here
can make a tree grow then everything
else does not here can make a tree grow
okay
the goal of this class either you fall
asleep or you're going out like damn
what's going on
I always thought seeds made trees but
just doesn't make sense something's
wrong okay you just didn't think about
it before it's not possible for a seed
to make a tree it's also not possible
for your husband to make you angry if
it's not possible for a state to make a
tree then it's not possible for your
husband to make you upset it's just
cause and effect didn't they have to
touch somewhere they have to touch right
they have to touch right and not sure
the kind of person is upset about
everything
I guess that's possible okay listen
let's make it easy if they're not both
there at the same time they cannot
affect each other
one cannot one ball cannot hit the other
ball okay if they are both there at the
same time
there's no cause and effect it's just
it's so basic it's hard to imagine okay
I'll say it again two balls cannot hit
each other if they're not there at the
same time but if the first ball is
creating the second ball then by
definition the second ball cannot be
there at the same time as the first ball
cause and effect is not possible there's
something yeah alex has got it look he's
like
well let's go on by the time the tree
grows this seed has to be gone but the
tree can't grow unless the seed touches
it but the seed can't be there at the
trees there and if the seed stir the
tree can't be there yet they have to
touch each other ok you should have a
headache by now now it should be
everything you should feel uncomfortable
if you feel uncomfortable you're on the
right track all right if you're just
uncomfortable cuz your butt hurts that's
a different thing
ok got it all right I'm not gonna say
more about that because I only have 5
more minutes okay his next argument is
okay what was that one what was that
about are they separate or not are they
yeah the first one was are they separate
or none but they both have to be there
to be separate second question yeah are
they similar or not
okay does the cause resemble the result
okay this is the second argument right
oh sorry you're right you're right okay
I'm confused
okay are they similar or not similar
here's the argument mmm
the definition of the four elements is
hard or wet or moving or temperature
those are the four energies okay those
are the four energies does your eyeball
have them
yeah it's physical okay now uh okay I'm
gonna take a little detour you need to
learn some Bobby dumber okay we're gonna
do it small I'll be done with class okay
this is what I'll be Dharma says all
physical things are either the elements
or something they have created all
physical things are either the four
elements or something they have created
got it and your eyeball is an example
okay your eyeball the cells in the back
of the eye our old friends the power the
indriya right is created by the four
elements okay
so here's something interesting in the
epidermis system okay just like in the
West stuff is made of molecules okay
your face your hand your foot your nose
is made of molecules the cells I'm made
of molecules the molecules are made of
atoms okay and in a typical atom I know
I've been doing this since high school
great school there should be some
protons there should be some neutrons
there should be electrons there's got to
be smaller things in the atom and they
make the atom and then you put atoms
together in different shells and you get
elements okay
and they different shells make them work
different ways same number atom protons
neutrons but in different shells then
the thing will work a different way okay
in the army Dharma okay and we won't
have time to go into number three but
you need some background and I have two
more minutes to give the background
right Tim two more minutes or I can cut
into yoga class fifty dollars if you
give me I will delay the yoga class
now I'm kidding thank you I don't want
to do that
according to OB Dharma all molecules
have eight atoms okay
have eight atoms okay four of them are
the four elements they gotta have one at
least one earth element atom they gotta
have one water element atom they gotta
have one fire element atom and they
gotta have one win element atom
got it that's easy it's like proton
Neutron electron okay or atoms different
atoms like h2o 2 hydrogen atoms for one
oxygen atom okay
in each molecule of water okay same and
I'll be done I said eight right then it
must have soup T Rho Rho say soup T Rho
vector
there's gotta be some physical sorry
there's gotta see something there's
gotta be a visible atom there has to be
an atom of visibility can be seen
something which can be seen okay how
many atoms got five yeah four elements
and now we got can be seen okay now
let's go down the body can be there has
to be one atom that's here something
here at boldness has to be in there it
has to be in there or you can't observe
it
okay sue did I say here I'll cancel that
one in the abhidharma we cancelled that
one okay
first Adam just atom number five
something you can see the RB Dharma
doesn't allow atoms of here both things
okay
why they so sudden you know pop they
just they just come and go like that
they don't stay so they say atoms don't
have that don't exception exception it
just so fast you can't put it in an atom
a molecule sorry molecules cannot have
sound atoms because it just goes and go
it cannot stay you can't make a chair
out of sound atoms it will fall down
then but that's okay don't blame me this
is a big honor talk to us and Stanley
Bundy
okay so fifth atom something you can see
six atoms something you go down go down
something you can smell there should be
a smell smell ability and then there
should be a taste ability and there
should be a touch ability okay let's
leave it at that then I have to teach
you more about it okay this is our be
dumber this is not every molecule of
everything physical thing must have
eight items four elements and four of
the five senses because sound is too
unsteady to make things okay got it
are you asking a question or you guys
Russ or you're gonna throw something at
me
okay all right let's stop there my goal
is to confuse you every class by the way
the abhidharma guys are not stupid we
are making fun of them but they're not
stupid they are extremely sophisticated
so think about it today you know think
about a molecule think about a
abhidharma molecule why does it have to
have solidity wetness temperature and
motion and why does it have to have
something you can about it you can see
something you can smell taste or feel
and that's physical reality
that's the their definition of physical
reality I could say the last four are it
must be observable by a human being by a
living being
okay the molecule must be perceivable by
the senses of a living beam and then
it's physical got it
that's a little cooler that's more cool
that's not so stupid right there's got
to be something smellable to be detected
by the nose there has to be something
testable to be detected there must be
something in the atoms of food that
tastes sweet or something there must be
okay that's their idea okay now last
thing mr. DeMarcos cosas
la causa ultima cosas like in in in
mexico they call me mr. lasting all
physical things according to the Ovid
armor must have molecules with those
eight atoms all physical things now I'll
leave you with a question okay when you
take a vow which we're gonna take some
heavy vows this week I'm gonna make some
full nuns which is very unusual I do it
like every ten years or something
according to the abbe Dharma what
happens you get a halo the nun when I
snap my finger in the vow now is it the
beginning of the fingers never and is it
separate from the any then a cosmic
picture is taken and they get a halo
they get this physical halo if you're
Buddha you can see it you know if you're
not a Buddha you know you can't tell if
the person's a monk or nun if they don't
have their clothes on and they didn't
get burned on their head okay bhana
which was a smart idea otherwise you
can't tell but if you're a Buddha
because she's a nun yeah how do you know
if she's got a miniskirt on she got a
halo I can see the halo is it physical
it is physical according to Abby Dharma
it's physical yan on communicating form
does it have those molecules that's one
question okay now the other question
then I'm gonna stop how many of those
eight atoms in the molecule are elements
and how many are products of elements
four and four four and four okay so
according to Abby Dharma all physical
things are made of molecules and every
single molecule has causes and results
in it every single molecule ate a atoms
there's four atoms of the causes and
there's four atoms of products of the
causes okay so I'm not just saying your
Skanda your Rupa now you know Sanskrit
you're I'm not just saying your physical
body has the elements and it's a
creation of the elements I'm saying
every single molecule in your body has
both
according to Buddha so don't tell me
their separator and they're not separate
I don't care
Buddha said every molecule of your body
has both got it we're not talking in
general your body your nose was made by
the foot we're not talking about that
every molecule in every cell in your
body has both the gardener if you say
they don't exist you're crazy you're
really crazy okay and trust me he was he
got a lot of massages in his life you
understand he got a lot of criticism if
you think you get criticized you should
be in the gardener he got criticized
okay
still criticized all right Bryan let's
go
[Music]
[Laughter]
yeah buddy some Yashin the big day my
talk on I've got shin my chair by Sean
it on voters at night man
did some Amish a tautology tsunami a
nature number per year